<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xml:id="sec-disnix-activate">
          
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>disnix-activate</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
		<refmiscinfo class="source">Disnix</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="version"><xi:include href="version.txt" parse="text" /></refmiscinfo>
	</refmeta>
	
	<refnamediv>
		<refname>disnix-activate</refname>
		<refpurpose>Activate a configuration described in a manifest</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>
	
	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>disnix-activate</command>
			<arg><replaceable>options</replaceable></arg>
			<arg choice="plain"><replaceable>manifest</replaceable></arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>
	
	<refsection>
		<title>Description</title>
		
		<para>
			The command <command>disnix-activate</command> will activate all the services in the given manifest
			file on the target machines in the right order, by traversing the inter-dependency graph
			of the services.
		</para>
		<para>
			If there is already a configuration deployed, then this command will perform an upgrade. 
			First it deactivates all obsolete services which are not present in the new configuration,
			finally it will activate all the new services in the new configuration. During this
			phase it takes inter-dependencies into account, so that no service will fail due to
			a broken inter-dependency closure.
		</para>
		<para>
			In case of a failure, a rollback is performed and all the newly activated services
			are deactivated and all deactivated services are activated again.
		</para>
		<para>
			Most users don't need to use this command directly. The <link linkend="sec-disnix-env"><command>disnix-env</command></link>
			command will automatically invoke this command to activate the new configuration.
		</para>
	</refsection>
	
	<refsection>
		<title>Options</title>
		
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>--interface</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Path to executable that communicates with a Disnix interface. Defaults to
						<link linkend="sec-disnix-ssh-client"><command>disnix-ssh-client</command></link>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>-p</option>, <option>--profile</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Name of the profile in which the services are registered. Defaults to: default
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>-o</option>, <option>--old-manifest</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Path to the manifest of the previous configuration. By default this tool will use the manifest
						stored in the disnix-coordinator profile instead of the specified one, which is usually sufficient
						in most cases.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>--coordinator-profile-path</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Nix profile path where the manifest should be stored, so that Disnix knows the current configuration
						of a distributed system. By default it is stored in the profile directory of the user.
						Most users do not want to use this option directly, but it is used by e.g. the virtualization
						extension to store virtual machine profile in a separate directory.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>-no-coordinator-profile</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By enabling this option Disnix does not store the deployment state for further use, such as upgrading.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>--no-target-profiles</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By enabling this option Disnix does not create profiles on the target machines containing the
						services.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>--no-upgrade</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By enabling this option Disnix will not perform an upgrade, but only activates services in the
						new configuration.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>--no-lock</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By enabling this option Disnix will not acquire any locks, which is not recommended.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			

			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>-h</option>, <option>--help</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Shows the usage of this command to the user.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>	
		</variablelist>
	</refsection>
	
	<refsection>
		<title>Environment variables</title>
		
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>DISNIX_CLIENT_INTERFACE</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Sets the client interface (which defaults to
						<link linkend="sec-disnix-ssh-client"><command>disnix-ssh-client</command></link>)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>DISNIX_PROFILE</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Sets the name of the profile that stores the manifest on the coordinator machine and the deployed
						services per machine on each target (Defaults to: default).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsection>
</refentry>
