<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-introduction">

<title>Installation</title>

<section>
<title>Obtaining Disnix</title>

<para>
The easiest way to use Disnix is by installing the Disnix package with
the Nix package manager from the
<link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixpkgs">Nixpkgs</link>
repository by typing:

<screen>
$ nix-env -i disnix
</screen>

Another way is downloading the Disnix source distribution
and to compile it manually. 
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Prerequisites</title>

<para>
In order to build Disnix the following dependencies are required
(only required if Disnix is built from source code):
Disnix uses XML for representing the lower level data formats and
therefore requires
<link xlink:href="http://www.xmlsoft.org">libxml2</link>
and
<link xlink:href="http://www.xmlsoft.org">libxslt</link>
to parse and transform them.

The Disnix service that provides remote access to deployment operations
is a D-Bus service and requires
<link xlink:href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/DBusBindings">dbus-glib</link>
(which itself depends on
<link xlink:href="http://www.gtk.org">GLib</link>
and
<link xlink:href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/dbus">D-Bus</link>
).
</para>

<para>
In order to run a Disnix client, the
<link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nix">Nix package manager</link>
must be installed, a copy of
<link xlink:href="http://nixos.org/nixpkgs">Nixpkgs</link> is required
and an environment variable NIXPKGS_ALL must point to the path where
it is installed.
</para>

<para>
By default, Disnix includes a SSH client and wrapper that can be used
to execute remote deployment operations. If you want to use SSH as a 
communication protocol, a
<link xlink:href="http://www.openssh.org">OpenSSH</link>
server must be running on each target machine and a client machine
requires a OpenSSH client.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Compiling Disnix</title>

<para>
After unpacking or checking out the Disnix sources, it can be
compiled by executing the following commands:

<screen>
$ ./configure <replaceable>options...</replaceable>
$ make
$ make install
</screen>

</para>

<para>
When building from the Subversion repository, these should be
preceded by the command:

<screen>
$ ./bootstrap
</screen>

</para>

<para>
The installation path can be specified by passing the
<option>--prefix=<replaceable>prefix</replaceable></option> to
<command>configure</command>. The default installation directory is
<filename>/usr/local</filename>. You can change this to any location
you like.  You must have write permission to the
<replaceable>prefix</replaceable> path.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Running a Disnix service on a target machine</title>
</section>

<para>
In order to deploy a distributed system in a network of machines, every
machine needs to be reachable by the coordinator, in order to perform deployment
steps remotely.
The Disnix service is a service that provides access to these operations
through a RPC protocol.
</para>

<para>
The Disnix service consists of two parts. A core Disnix component which actually performs
the deployment operations and a wrapper which exposes the operations to remote users
through a RPC protocol (such as the SSH wrapper which is included in the
Disnix distribution).
</para>

<para>
The core Disnix service is a D-Bus service operating on the system bus,
thus it requires the D-Bus system daemon running.
Moreover, it also requires the Disnix service configuration file
(which installed in PREFIX/etc/dbus-1/system.d) in the right location
so that it is allowed to register itself on the system bus with the right access permissions
(on most systems this location is in /etc/dbus-1/system.d).
</para>

<para>
Except for the core Disnix service, a protocol wrapper is required that provides remote
access to the core service operations through a RPC protocol. A SSH wrapper is included
which only requires a OpenSSH server running on the same machine. For other protocols,
you have to read the documentation that is included with the extension.
</para>

<para>
By default, only users who are members of the group 'disnix' may access operations
of the core Disnix service. Thus in order to access the Disnix operations remotely, either
an account with the right permissions is required or the protocol wrapper should perform
the authentication to the core Disnix service. The OpenSSH wrapper, for instance,
uses the credentials of the calling user from the coordinator by default
and therefore every target machine requires
the user to be defined in /etc/passwd and the user should be member of
the 'disnix' group.
</para>

</chapter>
