<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="chap-packages">

	<title>Using Disnix as a remote package deployer</title>

	<para>
		As described in the previous chapters, Disnix's primary purpose is deploying <emphasis>systems</emphasis> that
		can be decomposed into <emphasis>services</emphasis> to networks of machines.
		However, a service deployment process is basically a superset of an "ordinary" package deployment process.
		This chapter describes how we can do remote package deployment by instructing Disnix to only use a relevant
		subset of features.
	</para>

	<section>
		<title>Specifying packages as services</title>
		
		<para>
			In Nixpkgs, it is a common habit to write each package specification as a function in which the parameters
			denote intra-dependencies. In <xref linkend="chap-basicusage" /> we have shown that
			Disnix services follow the same convention and extend this approach with nested functions in which the inner
			function takes inter-dependencies into account.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			For services that have no inter-dependencies, a Disnix expression is identical to an ordinary package expression.
			This means that, for example, an expression for a package such as the Midnight Commander
			shown in <xref linkend="ex-package-expr" /> is also a valid Disnix
			service with no inter-dependencies:

			<example xml:id="ex-package-expr">
				<title>An example package expression and service expression with no inter-dependencies</title>
<programlisting>
{ stdenv, fetchurl, pkgconfig, glib, gpm, file, e2fsprogs
, libX11, libICE, perl, zip, unzip, gettext, slang
}:

stdenv.mkDerivation {
  name = "mc-4.8.12";

  src = fetchurl {
    url = http://www.midnight-commander.org/downloads/mc-4.8.12.tar.bz2;
    sha256 = "15lkwcis0labshq9k8c2fqdwv8az2c87qpdqwp5p31s8gb1gqm0h";
  };

  buildInputs = [ pkgconfig perl glib gpm slang zip unzip file gettext
      libX11 libICE e2fsprogs ];

  meta = {
    description = "File Manager and User Shell for the GNU Project";
    homepage = http://www.midnight-commander.org;
    license = "GPLv2+";
    maintainers = [ stdenv.lib.maintainers.sander ];
  };
}  
</programlisting>
		      </example>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Composing packages locally</title>

		<para>
			Package and service expressions are functions that do not specify the versions or variants
			of the dependencies that should be used. To allow services to be deployed, we must
			<emphasis>compose</emphasis> them by providing the desired versions or variants of
			the dependencies as function parameters.
		</para>
		<para>
			As shown in <xref linkend="chap-basicusage" /> we have to compose a Disnix service twice --
			first its intra-dependencies in a composition expression and later its inter-dependencies in the
			services model.
		</para>
		<example xml:id="ex-packages-composition">
			<title>Composing packages locally</title>
			
			<programlisting>
{pkgs, system}:

let
  callPackage = pkgs.lib.callPackageWith (pkgs // self);

  self = {
    pkgconfig = callPackage ./pkgs/pkgconfig { };

    gpm = callPackage ./pkgs/gpm { };

    mc = callPackage ./pkgs/mc { };
  };
in
self
			</programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>
			<xref linkend="ex-packages-composition" /> composes the Midnight Commander package by providing its intra-dependencies
			as function parameters. The third attribute (<varname>mc</varname>) invokes a function named: <code>callPackage {}</code>
			that imports the previous package expression and automatically provides the parameters having the same names as the
			function parameters.
			The <code>callPackage { }</code> function first consults the <varname>self</varname> attribute set
			(that composes some of Midnight Commander's dependencies as well, such as <varname>gpm</varname> and <varname>pkgconfig</varname>)
			and then any package from the Nixpkgs repository.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Writing a packages model</title>

		<para>
			Disnix provides first-class support to deploy packages to machines remotely. A <emphasis>packages model</emphasis> can be used to specify for each
			target machine in the network, which packages it should deploy as part of a Nix profile:
		</para>
		<example xml:id="ex-packages-model">
			<title>A packages model</title>

			<programlisting>
{pkgs, system}:

let
  customPkgs = import ./custom-packages.nix {
    inherit pkgs system;
  };
in
{
  test1 = [
    customPkgs.gpm
    customPkgs.mc
  ];

  test2 = [
    customPkgs.pkgconfig
  ];
}
			</programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>
			The <xref linkend="ex-packages-model" /> shows an example packages model that distributes GPM and Midnight Command to machine <varname>test1</varname>
			and <varname>pkgconfig</varname> to <varname>test2</varname>. Disnix will automatically instruct Nix to compile it for the corresponding system architecture
			of the target machine.
		</para>

		<para>
			In addition to a custom composition expression, you can also use the packages model to directly deploy packages from the Nixpkgs collection:
		<example xml:id="ex-packages-model-nixpkgs">
			<title>A packages model using packages from Nixpkgs</title>

			<programlisting>
{pkgs, system}:

{
  test1 = [
    pkgs.wget
  ];

  test2 = [
    pkgs.curl
  ];
}
			</programlisting>
		</example>

		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Deploying a packages model</title>

		<para>
			We can write an infrastructure model with target machines to remotely deploy packcages:
		</para>

		<example xml:id="ex-infrastructure-model-pkgs">
			<title>A basic infrastructure model for package deployment</title>
<programlisting>
{
  test1.properties.hostname = "test1";
  test2 = {
    properties.hostname = "test2";
    system = "x86_64-darwin";
  };
}
</programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>
			<xref linkend="ex-infrastructure-model-pkgs" /> describes two machines that have hostname <varname>test1</varname> and <varname>test2</varname>.
			Furthermore, machine <varname>test2</varname> has a specific system architecture: <code>x86_64-darwin</code> that corresponds to a 64-bit Intel-based Mac OS X.
		</para>

		<para>
			With the following command-line instruction the packages in the packages model can be deployed to the target machines defined in the infrastructure model:
<screen>
$ disnix-env -i infrastructure.nix -P packages.nix
</screen>
			The above command will build the packages from source code, distribute the packages and their dependencies to the target machines and switch the
			current symlink generations of the Nix profiles.
		</para>

		<para>
			Alternatively, packages can also be built on the target machines through Disnix instead of the coordinator machine:
<screen>
$ disnix-env --build-on-targets -i infrastructure.nix -P packages.nix
</screen>
		</para>

		<para>
			It is also possible to combine a packages model with the traditional three Disnix input models:
<screen>
$ disnix-env -s services.nix -i infrastructure.nix -d distribution.nix -P packages.nix
</screen>
			When combining a packages model with the traditional three Disnix models, it
			is possible to deploy additional supplemental packages in conjunction with
			the services that Disnix deploys.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Writing a minimal services model for deploying packages</title>
		
		<para>
			In addition to a packages model that specifies which packages to install on each target machine in the network, it is also possible
			to expose services in the services model as "ordinary" packages by annotating them with a <varname>type</varname> that refers to
			<varname>package</varname>. This could be useful to slowly migrate a deployment process that is package-based to a service-based deployment process.
		</para>

		<para>
			Services that are exposed as packages can also have inter-dependencies on services allowing you to deploy a client that automatically
			connects to a backend service.
		</para>

		<para>
			<example xml:id="ex-package-as-service">
				<title>Exposing a package as a service</title>

<programlisting>
{pkgs, system, distribution, invDistribution}:

let
  customPkgs = import ./custom-packages.nix {
    inherit pkgs system;
  };
in
{
  mc = {
    name = "mc";
    pkg = customPkgs.mc;
    type = "package";
  };
}
</programlisting>
			</example>

			In <xref linkend="ex-package-as-service" /> we import our intra-dependency composition expression 
			and we use the <varname>pkg</varname> sub attribute to refer to the intra-dependency composition of the Midnight Commander.
			We annotate the Midnight Commander service with a <code>package</code> type to instruct Disnix that no additional deployment
			steps need to be performed beyond the installation of the package, such activation or deactivation.
		</para>

		<para>
			Since the above pattern is common to all packages, we can also automatically <emphasis>generate</emphasis> services for
			any package in the composition expression, as shown in <xref linkend="ex-all-packages-as-services" />:

			<example xml:id="ex-all-packages-as-services">
				<title>Exposing all locally composed packages as services</title>

<programlisting>
{pkgs, system, distribution, invDistribution}:

let
  customPkgs = import ./custom-packages.nix {
    inherit pkgs system;
  };
in
pkgs.lib.mapAttrs (name: pkg: {
  inherit name pkg;
  type = "package";
}) customPkgs
</programlisting>
			</example>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Deploying packages</title>

		<para>
			By providing an infrastructure model and distribution model, we can use Disnix to deploy services exposed as packages to remote machines.
		</para>

		<example xml:id="ex-distribution-model-pkgs">
			<title>A basic distribution model for package deployment</title>

<programlisting>
{infrastructure}:

{
  gpm = [ infrastructure.test1 ];
  pkgconfig = [ infrastructure.test2 ];
  mc = [ infrastructure.test1 infrastructure.test2 ];
}
</programlisting>
		</example>
		<para>
			In <xref linkend="ex-distribution-model-pkgs" />, we distribute package <varname>gpm</varname> to machine
			<varname>test1</varname>, <varname>pkgconfig</varname> to machine <varname>test2</varname> and <varname>mc</varname>
			to both machines.
		</para>
		<para>
			When running the following command-line instruction:
<screen>
$ disnix-env -s services.nix -i infrastructure.nix -d distribution.nix
</screen>
			Disnix executes all activities to get the packages in the distribution model deployed to the machines, such as
			building them from source code (including its dependencies), and distributing their dependency closures to the target machines.
			Because machine <varname>test2</varname> may have a different system architecture as the coordinator machine, Disnix can
			use Nix's delegation mechanism to forward a build to a machine that is capable of doing it.
		</para>
		<para>
			Alternatively, packages can also be built on the target machines through Disnix:
<screen>
$ disnix-env --build-on-targets -s services.nix -i infrastructure.nix -d distribution.nix
</screen>

		</para>
		<para>
			After the deployment above command-line instructions have succeeded, we should be able to start the Midnight Commander
			on any of the target machines, by running:
<screen>
$ mc
</screen>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Configuring the remote machine's search paths</title>

		<para>
			To allow users on the remote machines to conveniently access their packages, we must add Disnix' Nix profile to the <envar>PATH</envar> of a user on the remote machines:
<screen>
$ export PATH=/nix/var/nix/profiles/disnix/default/bin:$PATH
</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			When using NixOS, this variable can be extended by adding the following line to <filename>/etc/nixos/configuration.nix</filename>:
<screen>
environment.variables.PATH = [ "/nix/var/nix/profiles/disnix/default/bin" ];
</screen>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Deploying any package as a service from the Nixpkgs repository</title>
		
		<para>
			Besides exposing custom packages as a service, it is also possible to use Disnix to remotely deploy any package in the
			Nixpkgs repository as a service, but doing so is a bit tricky. The main challenge lies in the fact that the Nix packages set is
			a nested set of attributes, whereas Disnix expects services to be addressed in one attribute set only.
		</para>
		<para>
			Fortunately, the Nix expression language and Disnix models are flexible enough to implement a solution.
			
			<example xml:id="ex-distribution-model-nixpkgs">
				<title>A distribution model referring to packages in Nixpkgs</title>
<programlisting>
{infrastructure}:

{
  mc = [ infrastructure.test1 ];
  git = [ infrastructure.test1 ];
  wget = [ infrastructure.test1 ];
  "xlibs.libX11" = [ infrastructure.test1 ];
}
</programlisting>
			</example>

			<xref linkend="ex-distribution-model-nixpkgs" /> shows a distribution model mapping a number of packages from the
			Nix packages repository to machines in the network. Note that we use a dot notation: <code>xlibs.libX11</code> as an
			attribute name to refer to <varname>libX11</varname> that can only be referenced as a sub attribute in Nixpkgs.
		</para>

		<para>
			We can write a services model that uses the attribute names in the distribution model to refer to the
			corresponding package in Nixpkgs:

			<example xml:id="ex-services-model-nixpkgs">
				<title>A services model referring to packages in Nixpkgs</title>
<programlisting>
{pkgs, system, distribution, invDistribution}:

pkgs.lib.mapAttrs (name: targets:
  let
    attrPath = pkgs.lib.splitString "." name;
  in
  { inherit name;
    pkg = pkgs.lib.attrByPath attrPath
      (throw "package: ${name} cannot be referenced in the package set")
      pkgs;
    type = "package";
  }
) distribution
</programlisting>
			</example>

			With <xref linkend="ex-services-model-nixpkgs" /> we can deploy any Nix package to any remote machine with Disnix.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Multi-user package management</title>

		<para>
			Besides supporting single user installations, Nix also supports <emphasis>multi-user installations</emphasis>
			in which every user has its own private Nix profile with its own set of packages. With Disnix we can also
			manage multiple profiles. For example, by adding the <replaceable>--profile</replaceable> parameter, we can
			deploy another Nix profile that, for example, contains a set of packages for the user: <code>sander</code>:
<screen>
$ disnix-env -s services.nix -i infrastructure.nix -d distribution.nix --profile sander
</screen>
			The user: <code>sander</code> can access its own set of packages by setting the <envar>PATH</envar>
			environment variable to:
<screen>
$ export PATH=/nix/var/nix/profiles/disnix/sander:$PATH
</screen>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
